A Finding Aid to the Mildred Baker Papers in the Archives of American Art AAA.bakemild
Archives of American Art
Mildred Baker papers
1882
1923-1997
AAA.bakemild
Archives of American Art
2.7 Linear feet
The papers of arts administrator Mildred Baker measure 2.7 linear feet and date from 1882 to 1997, with the bulk of the material dating from 1923 to 1997. Found within the papers are biographical materials; personal and professional correspondence; writings; files related to her work on the WPA Federal Art Project and other institutional art projects; printed material; photographs of Baker; and photographs and papers related to the work of her husband, Jacob Baker, who also administered programs for the WPA.
Baker, Mildred, 1905-
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Mildred Baker donated her papers in several increments between 1971 and 1993. In 1999, the bulk of her papers were donated to the archives by Baker's estate executor, Patricia Haskell, some of which included materials that had been loaned for microfilming in 1963.
Separated Materials note
Originals of loaned material, including exhibition catalogs and clippings, were returned to Mildred Baker after microfilming. Loaned materials are available on reel D110 but are not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art holds several collections related to Mildred Baker and the WPA Federal Art Project. There are two oral histories with Mildred Baker, one conducted by Harlan Phillips, September 21, 1963 and another by William Agee, July 22, 1965. There is also an oral history with Jacob Baker conducted by Harlan Phillips, September 25, 1963. Transcripts of the interviews conducted by Harlan Phillips are found within the collection. Collections related to the Federal Art Project include the Federal Art Project of the Work Projects Administration records and the Holger Cahill papers.
Existence and Location of Copies note
A small portion of the papers are also available on legacy 35 mm microfilm reel 1817 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. The Jacob Baker interview with Tex Goldchmidt was digitized for research access in 2009 and is available at the Archives of American Art offices. Researchers may view the original sound discs for the archival notations on them, but original discs are not available for playback due to fragility.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical/Historical note
Mildred Baker (1905-1998) was an arts administrator who worked in New York City, New York; Newark, New Jersey; and Washington, D.C.
Baker was born in Brooklyn, New York to composer and musician George Weiss and his wife Sophia Soennichsen, whose family were also musicians and writers. In 1925, while enrolled at the University of Rochester, she married the artist Ernest Holzhauer and together they moved to Europe for study and travel. In 1927, they returned to New York where Baker began working in administrative positions for the Van Diemen Galleries and the College Art Association. In 1934, she was hired by Holger Cahill to assist him in organizing Rockefeller Center's Salons of America Exhibition and First Municipal Art Exhibition. After the success of these shows, in 1935, Baker was hired as Cahill's assistant after he was selected to run the Federal Art Project for the Work Projects Administration in Washington, D.C.
While working for the Federal Art Project, Baker was appointed director of exhibitions and surveyed the work of over 100 art centers, organized over 500 traveling exhibitions, and managed the final allocation of artworks created for the FAP. In 1940, Baker divorced Mr. Holzhauer and married Jacob Baker, an economist and WPA administrator, union organizer, and a founder of the left-wing Vanguard Press, in 1947. After overseeing the closing of the Federal Art Project offices in Washington, Baker and her husband moved back to New York and became longtime residents of the Chelsea Hotel. Baker joined the staff of the Newark Museum in 1944, was promoted to assistant director in 1949, and to associate director in charge of exhibitions and programs from 1953 until her retirement in 1971.
In 1963, Baker was appointed by Governor Richard Hughes to the Commission to Study the Arts in New Jersey, and while serving as vice chairman, she oversaw the establishment of the New Jersey State Council on the Arts. She was a member of the Cosmopolitan Club, Women's City Club, Woman Pays Club, and American Association of Museums. Baker died on December 9, 1998.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of arts administrator Mildred Baker measure 2.7 linear feet and date from 1882 to 1997, with the bulk of the material dating from 1923 to 1997. Found within the papers are biographical materials; personal and professional correspondence; writings; files related to her work on the WPA Federal Art Project and other institutional art projects; printed material; photographs of Baker; and photographs and papers related to the work of her husband, Jacob Baker, who also administered programs for the WPA.
Biographical materials include birth and award certificates, curriculum vitae, divorce documents, an oral history transcript, and genealogical research and information on Baker's family, including her brother, the composer and bassoonist Adolph Weiss.
Correspondence is primarily with Baker's friends, business associates, researchers, and art institutions discussing personal relationships, research inquiries into the administration of the Federal Art Project, and loans and gifts of artwork to various institutions. The series includes Baker's responses to researcher requests regarding FAP exhibitions, programs, artists, and recollections of her fellow administrators.
Writings by Baker consist of reminiscences, 8 travel diaries, 3 essays, an exhibition catalog introduction, 4 lectures, and miscellaneous notes. Writings by others consist of 4 essays on contemporary art and art administration.
Federal Art Project files include correspondence; artist and exhibition lists; memoranda and general information; reports; speeches; information and photographs related to regional art centers and black artists; printed material; and miscellaneous material related to the Index of American Design, Southern California Art Project, and the Technical Services Laboratory.
General project files include information for 4 exhibitions, including the 1934 First Municipal Art and Salon of America Exhibitions; reports and speeches for the Newark Museum; information on the commissioning of the New Jersey Council on the Arts; and member information from the Woman Pays Club.
Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, newsletters, press releases, and a commercial recording of Alice Tully Hall.
Photographs are of Mildred Baker, including photos during her tenure at the Federal Art Project and Newark Museum. There is also a photograph of fellow FAP administrator Audrey McMahon.
Materials related to Jacob Baker include interview recordings and transcripts; personal correspondence with friends and business associates; writings and speeches; information related to Baker's work for the United Federal Workers of America; printed materials; and photographs of Baker.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1882, 1934-1990 (7 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1937-1997 (0.4 linear feet, Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1940-1985 (17 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Federal Art Project, WPA, circa 1934-1953 (0.8 linear feet, Box 1-2)
Series 5: Project Files, 1934-1991 (0.4 linear feet, Box 2)
Series 6: General Printed Material, 1923-1996 (11 folders; Box 2-4)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1934-1992 (2 folders; Box 3)
Series 8: Jacob Baker, 1930-1975 (0.3 linear feet; Box 3-4)
Baker, Jacob; Federal Art Project; Index of American Design; McMahon, Audrey, 1900?-1981; New York (N.Y.). Municipal Art Committee.; Newark Museum; Salons of America, Inc.; Technical Services Laboratory (National Space Technology Laboratories).; United Federal Workers of America.; Weiss, Adolph, 1891-1971; Art--Exhibitions--New York (State)--New York; Arts administrators; Federal aid to the arts; Interviews; Photographs; Transcripts
- Biographical Materials, 1882; 1934-1990; Series 1; 7 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include birth and award certificates, curriculum vitae, divorce documents, a voting card, and an oral history transcript of Baker's interview with Harlan Phillips in 1963 discussing her work with the Federal Art Project. There is also genealogical research and information on Baker's family, including her three brothers and sister. Information on her brother, the composer and bassoonist Adolph Weiss, includes his travel diary from tours to Asia and Europe during the 1960s.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Birth Certificate and Voting Card, 1967, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1953-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Divorce Papers, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family Genealogy, circa 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family, Siblings, 1882-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interview Transcript with Harlan B. Phillips, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, circa 1937-1997; Series 2; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is primarily with Baker's friends, business associates, researchers, art institutions, and admirers of her residency at the Chelsea Hotel.
  The series includes Baker's responses to researcher requests regarding FAP exhibitions, programs, artists, and recollections of her fellow administrators. Correspondence with Rutgers University, Francis O'Connor, Wendy Jeffers, and James Wechsler includes reports from their projects on the Federal Art Project, Holger Cahill, and Arthur Murphy and the WPA respectively. Correspondence with Robert Reiss includes an essay and research information on Sarah Freedman McPherson. There is also a letter from the writer Max Eastman describing the last days of his wife, Eliena Krylenko.
  Correspondence with the Archives of American Art, the Montclair Art Museum, Newark Museum, Roberson Center, Memorial Art Gallery, and the University of Wyoming record gifts and loans to these institutions from Baker's private collection.
  All correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - A Miscellaneous, circa 1970-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Archives of American Art, 1962-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - B-C Miscellaneous, circa 1968-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chelsea Hotel, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cowell, Sydney Robertson, 1970-1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Craft, Douglas, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - D-J Miscellaneous, circa 1954-1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jeffers, Wendy, 1987-1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - K-M Miscellaneous, circa 1949-1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mavigliano, George J., 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memorial Art Gallery, University of Rochester, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Montclair Art Museum, 1973-1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Museum of Early American Folk Art, 1966-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - N Miscellaneous, circa 1966-1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - National Collection of Fine Arts, 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - National Council on the Arts, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Newark Museum, 1954-1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Newark State College, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - O Miscellaneous, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - O'Connor, Francis, 1966-1996 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
  - P-Q Miscellaneous, circa 1967-1990 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Petteys, Chris, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - R Miscellaneous, circa 1937-1990 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Reiss, Robert, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Roberson Center for the Arts and Sciences, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - S Miscellaneous, circa 1966-1990 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Sherwood, Leland H., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - T-U Miscellaneous, circa 1968-1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Udell, Susan, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - University of Wyoming, 1975-1992 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - W Miscellaneous, circa 1960-1990 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Wechsler, James, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - White, John Franklin, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Writings, circa 1940-1985; Series 3; 17 Folders Box 1
  Writings by Baker consist of reminiscences, 8 travel diaries to Europe and the Middle East, 3 essays on the Federal Art Project and museum administration, an exhibition catalog introduction, 4 lectures on government patronage of the arts, and miscellaneous notes. Writings by others consist of 4 essays on contemporary art and art administration.
  - By Mildred Baker (Box 1)
    - Diary, General, circa 1960-1985 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Diary, Travel, 1972-1984 (Box 1, Folder 44-46)
    - Essay, "Consumer Demand for Today's Art", 1955 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Essay, "Exhibition Section of the Federal Art Project", circa 1940-1980 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Essay, "On Using Your Museum", circa 1950-1960 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Exhibition Catalog, On the Federal Art Project, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Lecture, At Artist's Club, circa 1950-1975 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Lecture, At University of Maryland, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Lecture, "Public and Private Art Patronage", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Lecture Introduction, At Artist's Club, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Notes, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - By Others (Box 1)
    - Goodrich, Lloyd, "Economics of Contemporary Art", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Kent, Henry W., "What I'm Pleased to Call My Education", circa 1950-1980 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Ripley, S. Dillon, "Museums in Today's Changing World", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Sinnick, A., "Modern Principles of Museum Administration", circa 1950-1970 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Federal Art project, WPA, circa 1934-1953; Series 4; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Federal Art Project files include correspondence to Mildred Holzhauer, Dorothy Miller, and Jacob Baker; artist and exhibition lists; department memoranda and general information; 8 reports; speeches; information and photographs related to regional art centers and black artists in 33 states; and clippings and news releases. The series also includes note cards and printed material related to the Index of American Design; a catalog and report produced by the Southern California Art Project; and general information, furniture blueprints, and circular publications produced by the Technical Services Laboratory.
  - Artist Biographies, circa 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Artist Lists, circa 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence, Mildred Holzhauer, Dorothy Miller, and Jacob Baker, 1936-1953 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Exhibition Allocations Lists, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Memorandum, Exhibition Unit, circa 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Memorandum, Exhibition and Allocations Unit, circa 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Report, "Art Project", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Report, "Brief Summary of the United States Government Art Projects", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Report, Conference on the Music, Writers' and Art Program, WPA, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Report, On the Federal Art Project, circa 1936-1943 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Report, "Relationship of the Federal Work Program to Unemployment", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Report, Sun Yat Sen, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Report, WPA Art Program, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Report, WPA Federal Art Project, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Speeches, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Art Centers, Memorandum and General Information, 1936-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Art Centers (AL, AZ, CA, CO, CT, DC, DE, FL, IL, IA, KS, MA, MD, MS, MT), 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Art Centers (NY, RI, OR, UT, VT, WA, WI), 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Art Centers, Photographs (AZ), 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Art Centers, Photographs (CA), 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Art Centers, Photographs (DC, FL, IA, IL, MI), 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Art Centers, Photographs (MN, MS, MT, NJ, NM), 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Art Centers, Photographs (NC, NY, OK, OR, SC), 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Art Centers, Photographs (UT, VA, WA, WI), 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Art Centers, Photographs, Scrapbook Pages, 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Art Centers, Photographs, Unidentified, 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Art Centers, Black Artists, Memorandum and Notes, circa 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Art Centers, Black Artists (AL, FL, IL, MI, NC, NY, OH, PA, TN, VA), circa 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Art Centers, Black Artists, Printed Materials, circa 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Art Centers, Black Artists, Photographs (DC, FL), circa 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Art Centers, Black Artists, Photographs (IL, MS, NC, VA), circa 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Index of American Design, Note Cards, circa 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Index of American Design, Press Releases, circa 1936-1942 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Index of American Design, Printed Material, 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Southern California Art Project, Catalog, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Southern California Art Project, Report, Southern California Creates, circa 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Technical Services Laboratory, General Information, circa 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Technical Services Laboratory, Blueprint Furniture Design, circa 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Technical Services Laboratory, Circulars (#3-5), 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Printed Material, Brochure, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Printed Material, Clippings, circa 1936-1949 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Printed Material, Press Releases, 1936-1939 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Project Files, 1934-1996; Series 5; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2
  General project files include information for 4 exhibitions, including a sales register for the First Municipal Art Exhibition and a photograph and catalog of the Salon of America Exhibitions; reports and speeches for the Newark Museum; and member information from the Woman Pays Club. The series also includes general information and three public hearing transcripts regarding the commissioning of the New Jersey Council on the Arts.
  Materials are arranged by subject and document type.
  - Exhibition, "Abstract Art, 1915 to Today" (1956), General Information (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition, "First Municipal Art," Sales Register, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition, "Salons of America," Catalog, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition, "Salons of America," Photograph of Artists and Staff, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition, "United States Building Exhibition," General Information, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Newark Museum, Reports, 1948-1956 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Newark Museum, Speeches, circa 1950, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - New Jersey State Council on the Arts, Correspondence, 1966-1975 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - New Jersey State Council on the Arts, General Information, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - New Jersey State Council on the Arts, Speeches, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - New Jersey State Council on the Arts, Public Hearing Transcript, 1965 September 14 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - New Jersey State Council on the Arts, Public Hearing Transcript, 1965 September 21 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - New Jersey State Council on the Arts, Public Hearing Transcript, 1965 September 29 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Woman Pays Club, Directories, 1974-1992 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Woman Pays Club, Member Information, 1984-1996 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- General Printed Material, 1923-1996; Series 6; 11 Folders Box 2-4
  Printed material includes general clippings, clippings featuring Mildred Baker, newsletters, press releases, and a commercial recording of Alice Tully Hall on sound disc (vinyl). There are also general exhibition announcements and catalogs, as well as catalogs and information on artists whose work Baker collected.
  - Clippings, 1923-1995 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Clippings on Mildred Baker, 1931-1996 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1934-1978 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, and Clippings, A-C, circa 1970-1985 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Artists whose work was purchased by Mildred Baker.
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, and Clippings, D-Z, circa 1970-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Newsletters, 1950-1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Press Releases, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1950-1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Recording, Alice Tully Hall at Lincoln Center, 1977; 1 Sound discs (vinyl) (Box 4)
- Photographs, circa 1934-1992; Series 7; 2 Folders Box 3
  Photographs are of Mildred Baker, including photos during her tenure at the Federal Art Project and Newark Museum. There is also a photograph of fellow FAP administrator Audrey McMahon.
  Materials are arranged by subject and chronological date.
  - Photographs of Mildred Baker, circa 1934-1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photograph of Audrey McMahon, circa 1937-1942 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Jacob Baker, 1930-1975; Series 8; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Materials related to Jacob Baker include personal correspondence with friends and business associates; writings and speeches on economics, management, and labor relations; finances, meeting minutes, member lists, and correspondence related to Baker's work for the United Federal Workers of America; clippings; and photographs of Baker. There is also an oral history transcript of Baker's 1963 interview with Harlan Phillips, and an interview recording with Tex Goldschmidt dating from the 1960s discussing his administrative work with the Federal Art Project on 4 sound discs (lacquer).
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  The Interview recording by Tex Goldschmidt has been digitized for research access.
  - Biographical Material, Interview Transcript with Harlan A. Phillips, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Biographical Material, Interview Recording with Tex Goldschmidt, circa 1960s; 4 Sound discs (lacquer) (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4.
  - Correspondence, A-Z, 1930-1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Condolences, 1963, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Writings and Speeches, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Project Files, United Federal Workers of America, 1937-1941 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Printed Material, Clippings, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Printed Material, Miscellaneous, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Jacob Baker, circa 1940-1967 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Oversized Interview Recording with Tex Goldschmidt, circa 1960s (Box 4)
    Oversized material from Box 3, F11.